Guide to the Simcha Blass Hydrology of Israel Collection
Department of Special Collections
Simcha Blass Hydrology of Israel collection
1935-1955
M1438
Blass, Simcha
5 linear ft. 6 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, 2 map folders
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Contains reports and other documents relating to the hydrology of Israel.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2004 (Accession 2004-167)
Custodial History
Collection was sold to a rare books dealer by an individual purporting to be an intermediary between the dealer and the Blass Family. The collection was subsequently purchased by Stanford University from the dealer.
Biography / Administrative History
Hydrological engineer and entrepreneur Simcha Blass was born in 1897 in Warsaw, Poland, the second of five children. As a boy, his education consisted of both religious and secular studies, and early on he developed a strong interest in engineering and also became intent on settling in the Jewish homeland. At the age of 17 he began his studies at the Wawelberg-Rotband mechanical-technical institute. In 1919 he was drafted and spent 18 months as a private in the Polish Army. After his discharge, he completed his studies and obtained an engineering credential.
A gifted engineer with a talent for invention, Blass spent most of the 1920s perfecting an implement for planting wheat that eventually increased crop yields by 300 percent. He saw this new device as a key to Jewish settlers' self-sufficiency. But he did not succeed in marketing his invention to investors and manufacturers and was particularly disappointed that it failed to take hold in Palestine. Eventually he came to realize that the main barrier to successful agricultural development and increased Jewish settlement in Palestine was the lack of a steady water supply, and his focus shifted to hydrological engineering.
Simcha Blass's involvement with the development of water resources, first in Palestine and then in the newly established State of Israel, began on a small scale. In the late 1920s, he settled in Deganyah Bet, a small agricultural community on Lake Kineret, and served as a consultant to several neighboring communities who had obtained funds from the Jewish Agency to install a pumping station to use Jordan River water for irrigation. His success in this project sparked a passion that would endure throughout his career. In 1930, Blass brought his wife from Bialystok, Poland and relocated to Tel Aviv, where he established a hydrological engineering firm. Over the next 30 years, Blass and his associates were key participants in the planning and construction of hydrological projects all over Israel, including the National Water Carrier. This ambitious project, completed in 1964, consists of a series of underground pipelines, open canals, reservoirs, and tunnels, which carry water from Lake Kineret to the Negev
Simcha Blass died in 1982, in Tel Aviv, Israel.
Sources:
Simhah Blas, Me merivah u-maas (Water in strife and action). Ramat-Gan: Masadah, 1973.
Dov Sitton, Development of water limited water resources: Historical and technological aspects. The American-Israeli Cooperative Enterprise, 2005. Retrieved from http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Environment/water.html
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains correspondence, maps, minutes, proposals and technical reports relating to the hydrology of Israel.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Savage, John Lucian, 1879-1967
Bibliography
Blas, Simcha Me merivah u-maas(Ramat-Gan: Masadah, 1973)
Sitton, Dov Development of water limited water resources: Historical and technological aspects(The American-Israeli Cooperative Enterprise, 2005)
Collection Contents
- Accounts, Series 1; 3 folders
  - Accounts (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Statements, invoices, and brief correspondence regarding accounts for Simha Blas's company Tikhnun ha-mayim le-yisrael ba"m [Israel Water Planning Ltd.]. 1954-1956.
  - Accounts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accounts (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Statements, invoices, and brief correspondence regarding accounts for Simha Blas's company Tikhnun ha-mayim le-yisrael ba"m [Israel Water Planning Ltd.]. 1952-1953.
- John Lucian Savage File, Series 2; 3 folders
  - J.L. Savage File (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Official file folder cover: Medinat yisrael misrade ha-memshalah: Savage. J.L. Savage was an American water engineer and consultant to various hydrological projects in Palestine/Israel.
  - J.L. Savage File (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Memo to J.L. Savage from the Water Department with questions concerning 1. All-Palestine Irrigation Scheme; 2. Medium Schemes in North; 3. Medium Schemes in South; 4. Secondary conduits; and 5. Power development. August 18th, 1949.
  - J.L. Savage File (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Three sets of handwritten notes regarding visit of American hydrology consultant J.L. Savage to Israel in August, 1949.
- Maps, Series 3; 3 folders, 1 flat box, 2 map folders
  - Mapat ha-geshamim/Rainfall map, by Dr. D. Ashbel (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Mapat ha-geshamim/Rainfall map: Palestine, Transjordan, Southern Syria, Southern Lebanon. D. Ashbel. Jerusalem: Hebrew University Press/Jewish Agency for Palestine. Ca. 1938.
  - Southern Palestine: geological map with explanatory notes. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Southern Palestine: geological map with explanatory notes. Shaw, S.H. Jerusalem: Government Printer, 1947. 42 p. with folded map.
  - Nikuz emek hefer: tokhnit atar. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Emek hefer drainage project: Site plan. Folded map too large for flat storage. Undated, ca. 1950s.
  - Maps (Othertype 8, Folder 1)
    Three maps: Admot reshut ha-huleh (lands of the Huleh authority), undated; Emek ha-huleh: baalut ha-karka ba-helek ha-deromi (Huleh Valley: land ownership in the southern region), June 18, 1942; Water research bureau: Eretz Israel catchment areas of individual brooks and wadis, 1936.
  - Maps (Othertype 8, Folder 2)
    Two maps: Emek yizrael ha-maaravi: skitsah li-virur haspakat mayim [Western Jezreel Valley; schematic to ascertain water supply]. Nov. 1935; Seker karkaot (ibud ve-hakhsharah) [land survey, Upper Galillee]. Jan. 1950.
  - Maps (Othertype 8, Folder 3)
    Two maps: Map of Palestine; Map of Palestine, copy 2. Undated.
  - Maps (Othertype 8, Folder 4)
    2 maps: Canal Jordan-KishonCanal Jordan-Kishon, copy 2. Undated.
  - Maps (Othertype 9)
    Four maps. Cultivable land on the Jordan Valley terrace. Undated;Litani and Upper Jordan rivers rainfall map. Sept. 9, 1943;Sekharim bi-levanon [dams in Lebanon]. Feb. 5, 1942;Untitled [Huleh area]. 1955.
  - Maps (Othertype 10)
    Five maps. Ezor ha-kevul [drainage area, Northern Huleh]. Nov. 20, 1955;Mapat ha-huleh [map of the Huleh area]. Undated.Mean annual rainfall. Undated.Palestine and adjoining territory. Oct. 9, 1943.Tokhnit yibush ve-nikuz shel ha-galil ha-elyon [plan for drainage and drying of the Upper Gallilee]. Undated.
  - Maps (Othertype 11)
    Nine maps. Amendments to the I.P.C. corridors. Jun. 8, 1945.Amendments to the I.P.C. corridors. Jun. 1945.Lake Hula. Jul. 1950.Mapat mahaneh shel mifal yibush ha-huleh [Camp map of the Huleh drainage (drying) project]. Dec. 7, 1955.Palestine administration map. Aug. 1936.Tokhnit emek zevulun/Town planning scheme Emek Zebulun area. Oct. 1936.Tokhnit yibush ha-huleh/ha-yarden ha-deromi, daf 1 [Huleh drainage project/southern Jordan, page 1].Tokhnit yibush ha-huleh/ha-yarden ha-deromi, daf 2 [Huleh drainage project/southern Jordan, page 2].Tokhnit yibush ha-huleh [Huleh drainage project]. All undated, ca. 1950s.Yarmuk diversion canal/Alignment of main canal. Undated.
  - Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim (Box 1, Folder 10)
    File folder cover: Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim: Mar [Mr.] Simha Blas.
- Meeting Minutes, Series 4; 11 folders
  - Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Minutes and other materials from meetings of the Water Board of the Ministry of Agriculture, Dec. 1960 - Feb. 1963.
  - Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Misrad ha-haklaut/moetset ha-mayim (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Vaadat ha-shiput (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Folder cover: Medinat yisrael misrade ha-memshalah: Vaadat ha-shiput [jurisdiction committee].
  - Vaadat ha-shiput (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Meeting minutes and related materials of the water department's Jurisdiction Committee. 1950-1952.
  - ha-Vaad le-tikhnun mifal ha-mayim ha-artsi. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Meeting minutes and related data for the water department's committee for planning of the national water plant. 1955.
  - ha-Vaad le-tikhnun mifal ha-mayim ha-artsi. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Meeting minutes and related data for the water department's committee for planning of the national water plant. 1952-1954.
  - ha-Vaad le-tikhnun mifal ha-mayim ha-artsi. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Meeting minutes and related data for the water department's committee for planning of the national water plant. 1950.
- Memoranda, Series 5; 3 folders
  - Memoranda (Box 2, Folder 7)
    3 memoranda: From Denver, CO hydrology consultants H.W. Bashore, J.L. Savage, and Abel Wolman to David Ben Gurion regarding the master plan for development of water projects in the State of Israel. 12 p. Dec. 10, 1950; A. Trisht to Meshek Sede Nehamiah regarding their pumping station. Dec. 22, 1953; Y. Trisht regarding digging of a reservoir at Bet Hashita. Dec. 13, 1967.
- Project Proposals, Series 6; 1 folder
  - Agudat ha-mayim ha-shitufit be-emek harod, Subseries 6.01; 1 folder
    - Nikuz agan ha-kavot nahal haderah (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Proposal and maps for collection basin drainage project, Nahal Haderah. 1956.
  - Bet Shean, Subseries 6.02; 4 folders
    - Bet Shean (Box 2, Folder 9)
      File folder cover: Medinat yisrael misrade ha-memshalah: Bet Shean.
    - Bet Shean (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Written proposals and data for Bet Shean valley water plant. 1950.
    - Blueprints (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Blueprints for Bet Shean valley water plant. 1950.
    - Blueprints (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Eilat, Subseries 6.03; 2 folders
    - Folder cover (Box 3, Folder 1)
      File folder cover: Medinat yisrael misrade ha-memshalah: Eilat.
    - Project proposal: Eilat (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Handwritten notes and data relating to water supply project for Eilat. 1951.
  - Emek ha-Yarden, Subseries 6.04; 10 folders
    - Project proposals: Emek ha-Yarden (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Notes and data relating to irrigation projects for the Jordan Valley. 1952.
    - Project proposals: Emek ha-Yarden (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Project proposal summary and blueprints for Masadah-Shaar ha-Golan and Helkat Tel Katsir water supply project: Connection to the Bet Zera reservoir. 1960.
    - Project proposals: Emek ha-Yarden (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Project proposal and blueprints for Masadah-Shaar ha-Golan and Helkat Tel Katsir water supply project: Connection to the Bet Zera reservoir. 1960.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Kevutsat Mesadah (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Blueprints and written proposals relating to three Kevutsat Mesadah water projects. 1955-1956.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Meshek Ein Gev (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Blueprints and written proposals relating to four Meshek Ein Gev water projects. 1955, 1958, 1959, 1962.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Kevutsat Alumot (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Blueprint relating to Kevutsat Alumot pump installation project. 1955.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Kevutsat Kineret (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Blueprints, notes, and proposal relating to Kevutsat Kineret water projects. 1956, 1962.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Bet Gordon (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Blueprint for Bet Gordon water supply project. 1955.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Kevutsat Afikim, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Blueprint for Kevutsat Afikim pump housing project.
    - Emek ha-Yarden: Tel Katsir, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Blueprint for Tel Katsir irrigation canal.
  - Emek Hefer, Subseries 6.05; 5 folders
    - Emek Hefer: Ein Hahoresh, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Blueprint and proposal for Ein Hahoresh water project.
    - Emek Hefer: Bet Herut, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Blueprints and proposals for two Bet Herut water projects.
    - Emek Hefer: Kefar Vitkin, 1958; 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Blueprints and proposals for four Kefar Vitkin water projects.
    - Emek Hefer: ha-Moetsah ha-ezorit, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Blueprint and project cost summary for Emek Hefer Area Council water project.
    - Emek Hefer: Kefar Hayim, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Blueprint and memo regarding Kefar Hayim water project.
  - Ein Harod, Subseries 6.06; 2 folders
    - Ein Harod: Berekhat adamah, July, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      File folder cover for Ein Harod earth pool project proposal. Misrad le-handasah hidraulit: S. Blas.
    - Ein Harod: Berekhat adamah, July, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Project proposal and blueprints for Ein Harod earth pool [reservoir] project.
  - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, Subseries 6.07; 5 folders
    - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, May, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      File folder cover for Maayan Barukh irrigation project proposal.
    - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, May, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Maayan Barukh irrigation project proposal and blueprint.
    - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Two brown envelopes for Maayan Barukh irrigation project proposal; one has pencil schematic on back.
    - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Notes, memos, and blueprints relating to Maayan Barukh irrigation project proposal.
    - Maayan Barukh tokhnit hashkaah, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mifal ha-galil ha-elyon, Subseries 6.08; 2 folders
    - Mifal ha-galil ha-elyon (Box 4, Folder 6)
      File folder cover: Mekorot: hevrat mayim ba"m: Mifal ha-galil ha-elyon. Upper Gallilee plant.
    - Mifal ha-galil ha-elyon, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Project proposal and blueprint for Upper Gallilee water plant project.
  - Mifal ha-galil ha-merkazi, Subseries 6.09; 2 folders
    - Mifal ha-gevul ha-tsefoni (Box 4, Folder 8)
      File folder cover. Mekorot: hevrat mayim ba"m. Northern border water plant.
    - Mifal ha-galil ha-merkazi, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Water supply project proposal for settlements on the Lebanon border.
  - Nikuz agan ha-kavot nahal haderah, Subseries 6.10; 2 folders
    - Agudat ha-mayim ha-shitufit be-emek harod (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Agudat ha-mayim ha-shitufit be-emek harod: aspakat mayim la-tsafon: tokhnit kelalit. Documents pertaining to the cooperative water union of Emek Harod: general plan for water supply to the Northern region. 1967.
  - Ramat ha-galil ha-tahton haspakat ha-mayim, Subseries 6.11; 2 folders
    - Ramat ha-galil ha-tahton haspakat ha-mayim (Box 4, Folder 11)
      File folder cover. Ramat ha-galil ha-tahton haspakat ha-mayim. Lower Gallilee water supply project.
    - Ramat ha-galil ha-tahton haspakat ha-mayim (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Lower Gallilee water supply project proposal and blueprint. Undated.
  - Tel Yosef berekhat adamah, Subseries 6.12; 2 folders
    - Tel Yosef berekhat adamah (Box 4, Folder 13)
      File folder cover. Tel Yosef berekhat adamah (Tel Yosef earth pool). 1935.
    - Tel Yosef berekhat adamah (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Proposal and blueprints for Tel Yosef earth pool construction. 1935.
  - Yarkon-Faluja conduit, Subseries 6.13; 2 folders
    - Yarkon-Faluja conduit (Box 4, Folder 15)
      File folder cover. Yarkon Faluja Conduit: Program of Development: Economic Analysis. File contents: project proposal, report, and blueprints. 1952.
    - Yarkon-Faluja conduit (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Blueprints relating to Yarkon-Faluja conduit project. 1953.
    - Yarkon-Faluja conduit (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Technical Reports, Series 7; .75 linear ft.
  - Closed conduits in reinforced concrete (Box 4, Folder 18)
    File folder cover. Closed conduits in reinforced concrete, I. Olexinzer.
  - Closed conduits in reinforced concrete, 1951; 52 p., 26 plates (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Closed conduits in reinforced concrete, part 1. I. Olexinzer. Jerusalem: Ministry of Agriculture, Water Department, Division of National Planning..
  - Eng[ineer] Fuks file, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Eng[ineer] Fuks file. Notes, data, and report on problems of development of water [resources] in Israel.
  - John S. Cotton report, 1950; 224 p. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Bound typewritten volume. John S. Cotton, Interim report on master plan for development of irrigation and hydroelectric power in State of Israel, Vol. I.
  - John S. Cotton report, 1951; 184 p. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Bound typewritten volume. John S. Cotton and James B. Hayes, Third interim report on master plan for development of irrigation and hydroelectric power in State of Israel, Vol. 1.
  - John S. Cotton report, 1951; 40 plates (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Bound typewritten volume. John S. Cotton and James B. Hayes, Third interim report on master plan for development of irrigation and hydroelectric power in State of Israel, Vol. 2.
  - Israel and its water resources, August 1956; 26 p. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Israel and its water resources: Facts and figures. Water Planning for Israel, Ltd.,
  - Mehir ha-mayim la-haklaut, April 1954; 30 p. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Mehir ha-mayim la-haklaut, me-et S. Blas. (The price of water for agriculture, by S[imha] Blas. ).
  - ha-Yarkon (Box 6, Folder 3)
    File folder cover. Medinat yisrael: misrade ha-memshalah. ha-Yarkon.
  - Mifal ha-Yarkon (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Handwritten notes and data on the Yarkon [river] water plant project. Undated.
  - Jordan and Litani river basins, Feb. 1954 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Plan for the development and utilization of the water resources of the Jordan and Litani river basins, vol. 2, by John S. Cotton, consulting engineer. Bound maps and blueprints.
  - Litani river project: Qaraoun reservoir, Aug. 1943. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Litani river project: Qaraoun reservoir: Mass curves. Graph. Palestine Water Co. Ltd.,
  - Some Information on Lake Tiberias (Box 6, Folder 7)
    File folder cover. Some Information on Lake Tiberias, report no. 2, by A. De Leeuw and M. Auerbach.
  - Some Information on Lake Tiberias, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Some Information on Lake Tiberias, report no. 2, by A. De Leeuw and M. Auerbach. 58 p. and appendices.
  - Some Information on Lake Tiberias (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Some Information on Lake Tiberias, [Incomplete copy; p. 38-59 plus appendices.] (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Some Information on Lake Tiberias, report no. 2, by A. De Leeuw and M. Auerbach.
  - The water resources of Israel, June 1952; 50 p. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    The Water resources of Israel. A survey by S. Blass, director, Water Department.
  - The water resources of Israel, June 1952; 50 p. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    The Water resources of Israel. A survey by S. Blass, director, Water Department. [This copy has typeset cover.]
- Photographs, Series 8; .25 linear ft.
  - Photographs: California (Othertype 7, Folder 1)
    Ten 3.5" x 4.5" black and white photographs taken in California, labeled Cucamonga [3]; Cucamonga spreading grounds; Sausage Dam Cucamonga spreading ground; San Gabriel [3]; Sierra Madre City of " "; Eaton Wash spreading grounds L.A.C.F.C.D. Undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Five 5" x 7" black and white photographs. One labeled Caesarea - Finished pumping installations, Sept. 1963. Four unidentified, undated.
  - Photographs, One 3" x 4" black and white photograph, unidentified, undated. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Three 2.5" x 3.5" black and white photographs. Labeled Nahal Iron shitafon, sof november 1964, hutsfu: ha-sadot, kevishim u-gesharim. [Iron river flooding end of November 1964, flooded: fields, roads and bridges]
  - Photographs: Huleh (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Four 3.5" x 5.5" black and white photographs. Labeled Huleh: karkaot ha-agam [Huleh lakebed]. Undated.
  - Photographs: Hulot Yavneh, Mar. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Six 3.5" x 5" black and white photographs. Five labeled Hulot Yavneh [Yavneh dunes], Feb. 1965.One labeled Nahal Adah - kevish Pardes Hanah Binyaminah shitfonot 1964/02 [Adah river Pardes Hanah-Binyaminah road flooded 1964/02.
  - Photographs: Europe (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Four black and white photographs (5 x 5", 3 x 3", 4 x 2", 3 x 2") of unidentified round six-story brick building (with Israeli flag flying on top) near railroad tracks. Stamp on back reads "de Graaf C572 Leiden." Undated. One 3.5 x 2.5" black and white photograph of girl posing on ice. Undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Five black and white photographs, 3.5 x 2.5", unidentified, showing concrete conduit construction.Two black and white photographs, 3,5 x 2.5", unidentified, showing retaining wall construction. All undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 8)
    One black and white photograph, 7 x 9.5", showing lab technician conducting experiment. Sign on machine reads: Nekez hupi: nisui ms. 15 [Shore drainage, experiment no. 15].
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Two black and white photographs. 8 x 6" shows worker standing on large drilling rig, undated.5 x 5" shows wetland, undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Six black and white photographs, 3.5 x 4.5" show a field being tilled. Undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Five black and white photographs, 3.5 x 2.5". Three show an unidentified body of water. Two show close and far view of the opening of a water conduit. Undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Six black and white photographs, 2.5 x 4", showing placement of concrete rings in ground using a crane. Photos numbered on back 6-11. Undated.
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Fourteen black and white photographs, 2.5 x 4", showing unidentified area, poss. Caesarea. All marked "3" in pencil on back. Undated.